[Music]
well
i welcome you all to the lecture four of
week five
in this week we will be studying the
important building block
of an automated system that is
microprocessor technology
let us look at the outline of this
lecture
at start of the lecture we will see the
definition of
a microprocessor
then we will see its architecture
it has various elements
how these elements operate
then we will learn what is the
difference between
a microcontroller and a microprocessor
the definition of microcontroller will
be studied
after that we will study
the microcomputers which we are using
for our regular day-to-day activities
at the end of the lecture we will study
about
the plcs the programmable logic
controllers
which are used in the automation
industry
its elements configuration and operation
will be studied in detail
fine let us begin in this lecture
we will be studying various programmable
logic devices
in a in our previous lectures we have
seen
the elements of measurement system
such as the sensors and
the signal conditioning devices
after that we have also seen how we can
convert the signals from one form to the
another form now let us look at
the fundamentals of programmable logic
devices
as the name suggests the programmable
logic devices
has two words
these are programmable and logic
the devices which are carrying out
logical operations on the data
are called as the logic devices
but when we are able to program them
when the users are able to program
these logic devices then we are call
them as
the programmable logic devices
programmable means
we can teach we can instruct
we can train these logic devices to
carry out
a certain set of instructions in
the given sequence
so what kind of operations these
programmable logical
logic devices are carrying out they are
carrying out various
control functions according to
the instructions written in its memory
so whatever the commands that we are
giving they are
the low level language commands
we will see what is the meaning of the
low level and the high level language
in the next few slides
the first pld is the microprocessor
microprocessor is a digital
integrated circuit it is
an electronic circuit and it carries out
various digital functions which are
necessary
to process the information which are
to process the data given to the
microprocessor
the microcomputer is
utilizing the microprocessor
as its cpu that is a central processing
unit
and it contains all functions of a
computer
so micro computer may have memory
it can communicate with the outside
world
with input output devices
so here you must know the difference
between
the processor and a computer processor
is a simple
circuit while computer is a system
it has processor as the cpu central
processing unit
third pld which is very
widely used which is very important as
far as
the automated system is concerned is
plc that is programmable logic
controller
programmable logic controller also
incorporates
the microprocessor as
the central processing unit and it
controls the operations
of electromechanical devices
but plc is working in very harsh
condition
so the construction of the plc must be
very rugged
very robust
the general microprocessors which are
used in
automation industry are the embedded
microprocessor
some of the features of this
are first
these kind of microprocessors are
dedicated to a specific function
control of a specific function for
example
we want to have an automatic control
system
to control the temperature of an
electric furnace
here the function is to control the
temperature of
the furnace if the temperature
if the inside temperature of the furnace
is above the set value
the microprocessor should cut off
the supply of electricity to that
electric furnace
so a simple electronic circuitry
which is embedded inside the electric
furnace
is nothing but the embedded
microprocessor
so it is dedicated to carry out specific
functions
second feature of the embedded
microprocessor is
they are self starting
so the processors are starting on their
own
as we switch on the system the processor
will start
on its own
why we are incorporating
the microprocessor is in automation as
we have seen
the definition of automation that we
want to
reduce the human intervention we want to
have no intervention
so to carry out the operations in auto
mode
we are taking help of the electronic
spec circuitry
that is nothing but the microprocessors
these are completely self-contained
the embedded microprocessor has their
own memory
has may have their own battery backup as
well
they may have their own energy source as
the microprocessor which are used in
automation
which are embedded in in the products or
systems
has their own operating system
so we can say an embedded microprocessor
will be dedicated to a specific function
it is self-starting it doesn't require
any human intervention
these are completely self-contained
everything is there inside the system
and they do have their own operating
system
the microprocessor a multi-purpose
programmable device
it basically reads the binary
instructions
from a storage device that called memory
the memory may be the temporary memory
or it may be
the permanent memory so whatever the
signals which are
getting in will be stored in a temporary
memory
the microprocessor process this
information
as per the need as per the instructions
given in the program
it process that information according to
the instructions
and it provides the results as
the output so getting
the information reading the information
and processing the information based
upon the instructions given
are the functions of a microprocessor
but how these functions are carried out
to carry out these functions the
microprocessor
basically has three elements
the processor memory element
and input output devices to carry out
these functions
the microprocessor basically has
hardware and this
and the hardware is nothing but the
electronic parts
which are integrated together to carry
out
the intended operation the processor is
an electrical circuitry
memory is an electronic part and
input output devices are are the
electromechanical
parts well these components are
integrated together
but their coordinated operation will be
carried out
by a set of instructions
and that of set of instruction is
nothing but the program
and when we group together
a variety of programs then we call that
as a
software
so let us see what this processor does
the processor recognizes the program
instructions
and it carry out it execute
that program instructions as per the
order given as per the sequence
given the microprocessor has the in
input output interfaces
so the microprocessor is also carrying
out the communication between
the cpu that is the processor and the
outside world
through the input output interfaces
so in general we call the interface as
port in our day to day language as well
we are using
the word port quite often
the third element which is there that is
a memory
the memory basically holds the program
instructions and the data
the applications of microprocessor can
be classified
basically in two categories so based
upon the applications of the
microprocessor
we can say that the microprocessor can
be utilized
as a reprogrammable system device
such as the microcomputer
so whatever the computing devices that
we do have
we can reprogram these systems we can
change its operating system
we can install some programs we can
modify
uh these programs we can edit the
programs
so to carry out these operations in
microcomputers
we are using the microprocessor
so when we are using the microprocessor
utility for developing the
reprogrammable system
that we call the application of
microprocessor
to have the microcomputers
in the second application we we want to
have
the dedicated functions that to be
carried out by the microprocessor
and these are nothing but the embedded
systems which we have already talked
about
let us consider the typical automated
system such as
a conveyor belt automated guided
vehicles
automatic furnaces
all the manufacturing industry equipment
whether it may be processing equipment
or it is
the conveying equipment or it is
the monitoring equipment so whenever we
are saying
we want to carry out the intended
application the desired application
in automatic mode there also
we need the microprocessor so the
application of microprocessor to carry
out
specific functions in automatic mode
that is nothing but the embedded system
these processors
do operate in binary digits that is
0 and 1 these digits are called bits
if the electrical voltage given to the
machine
is of low level then the bit would be 0
and if a high voltage is applied
high electrical energy is applied
then we are considering that as
the beat 1.
so when we group together these beads
a word is formed
and if the length of the word is 8 bits
then that
then we are calling that word as the
byte
if the word length is 4 then we are
calling that as
nibble
so as already i have talked to you a
command in binary
to accomplish a task is nothing but the
instruction
read write
add subtract
so so many operations the
microprocessors are carrying out
the command in binary to accomplish that
task
is nothing but the instructions that we
are giving to the microprocessor
so these instructions can be entered
either through input devices or they can
be stored
in the storage devices itself
so the instructions we can input by
using the keyboard
that is a very general input device that
we use
or we are using the pointing device and
clicking device
nothing but the pointer is nothing but
the mouse these are all
input devices but in in certain cases
the instructions are embedded they are
stored in the memory of the computer
itself
a typical architecture
of the microprocessor can be seen
on your screen so as i mentioned
it has the processor
the processor has three parts
first is arithmetic and logic unit
register arrays and the control unit
the second set of elements
is the input output devices
through which the microprocessors are
communicating with
the outside world
and the third element is the memory
so either we can have the read-only
memory
permanent memory or we can have
the random memory where we can read or
write
we can have the erasing operations
be possible so to communicate with these
input output devices
and the memory we required a mechanism
and that mechanism is nothing but the
communication mechanism
which is through the wires
through wires we are passing the
electrical signals
and a set of wires is nothing but the
bus through which
we are communicating with various
elements of the microprocessor
the resistor array has many resistors
and these resistors are
utilized as temporary memory locations
through which the microprocessor is
carrying out a variety of operations
what operations is it is carrying out it
is carrying out
the algebraic operations as well as the
logic operations so algebraic operations
are
the addition and subtraction and
the logic operations are and or
the input output devices are called the
peripherals
so when we have the central processing
unit
on a single chip that is called the
microprocessor
so as i mentioned the arithmetic and
logic unit
is carrying out the operations such as
addition
subtraction these are the algebraic
arithmetic
operations and the logic operations are
the and or operations
the register array is is having
a set of registers which are acting as
temporary storage devices so whatever
the
information we are getting from
the memory may be permanent or the
random access memory these information
will be stored in a temporary manner
inside the cpu itself
based on the control instructions
the microprocessor is taking this
information
which is at the temporary storage it
carries
out the arithmetic and logic operations
on this information which is
stored in the register arrays and it
further
gives the output which is stored in the
register array itself
so whatever the results are stored in
the register array
that will be taken through the bus
that will be communicated to the output
terminal if required or it will be
stored
inside the memory the control
unit is carrying out the controlling of
the signals or the data to
switch the data through the system bus
and apply the set of instructions
over the data would be controlled by
this control unit the timings will be
set
so it has a clock
it is nothing but a oscillator
oscillator circuit which we have seen in
our
the early lecture that is the
piezoelectric based
clocks the clocks are giving signals
the time has over now we have to execute
the next set of instruction
so accordingly the processor will take
the data
it will process the data and return the
data back to the register array
the peripherals the input
peripheral are nothing but
the keyboards or we can have
the adcs that is analog to digital
converters
we have seen in our previous class
that the analog to digital converters
are converting
the analog data into digital format
and that digital format data will be
given to the microprocessor
in case of it is used for the embedded
operations but if the microprocessor is
a part of a
microcomputer then we are inputting the
data
through the keyboard if
the microprocessor is utilized in a
microcontroller then the output would be
given to the actuating device
through the signal condition device such
as
dac that is a digital to analog
converter
but if it is a micro computer then the
output would be
simple display devices such as leds
crts or a printer or
a magnetic tape as i mentioned there are
two
types of memories are used that is a
read-only memory
and the random access memory
in read-only memory we are storing the
programs
which we cannot alter these are
the system programs which we are
storing the user cannot change the
programs
so some programs like the monitor
program
or the drivers of the hardware are
stored in
the read-only memory
the data on the random access memory can
easily be changed
here we are giving the data
that to be processed or even we can
have the programs that to be modify or
edit
so bus is nothing but a group of wires
which are used to
communicate the signals among the
various elements of
the microprocessor system after studying
the definition of a microprocessor
microcomputer now let us look at
the configuration of the microcomputer
on your screen you can see typical
arrangement of
a variety of elements of a microcomputer
so it has the alu
and control unit it has
the input output devices
these are the peripherals the memory
and various types of buses
these buses are carrying the digital
signals
from one section to another section
these are the paths through which we are
communicating either the data
related to the variable
the instructions to carrying out
the controlling operation or to
communicate
the address of the data
the bus is nothing but
collection of a number of parallel
conductors
these are carrying electrical signals
and these buses are being shared by
many chips which are integrated
in a typical micro computer so you
might have gone through various
configurations
of microcomputer
based upon the number of bits
so we can call a 16 bits configuration
or 32 bits configuration or
64 bits com configuration
the meaning is that we can handle
2 raised to power number of bits
values by using these
communication paths if the number of
bits are 16
that means we can handle 2 raised to
power
16 types of values by
using this communication path so as
the number of paths are more we can
have the faster communication
in earlier days there was a serial
communication in the microprocessor
the information or the instructions
used to pass in a sequential manner
so that's why the microprocessors were
very very slow
with the invention with the introduction
of
the parallel communication by using
these
wires now the microprocessors
are very fast very rapid
each path carries one bit of data
there are basically three types of buses
being used
in microprocessor or a micro computer
the first type of bus is the data bus
the data bus is associated with
processing of the information
if we are saying that there is a word
length of four bits
consider a word of one zero one zero
that means we require four parallel
wires
that to be laid down to communicate
this this word one zero one zero
so the number of values which can be
possible by using this 4 bit data bus
so we can have 2 raise to power 4 that
is
16 number of values can be handled by
this data so if you take example of a
embedded system which is used to
record forces and to process the
information about the forces
say automatic way balance machine
so when the force is in between
20 to 180 newton we are using this
device this is the the range of
the device is 22 or 80 newton
capacity the span would be 160
so as the number of values are only 16
so we can have only 16 segments
of the span so the 16 segments of the
span can be handled by
this microprocessor or the embedded
system
each segment may have a 10
newton of the capacity
the 4 bits type of data buses
or 4 bits type of the communication
systems
are quite often used in toys
so automatic toys very small
type of in very small variety of
information
we need to process but the general
computers that we are
using nowadays they do have the capacity
of 64 bit
maybe more than that
the next bus is the address bus it
carries the signal
which is indicating where the data
is to be find out so it carries
the location it carries the information
about the location of the data from
which we have to
fetch the data or we have to load the
data
or write the data in the memory
locations
select the certain memory location
at the input or output ports as well
it's not only getting the data from the
memory locations
at the memory in the memory each store
storage location has
a unique identification and that that
unique identification
is called the address the next type of
bus is the control bus
the control bus is carrying out
the signals related to the control
actions so what may be the control
action
say reading the data from the input
device
it's basically the function of
the microprocessor read the data
so it is controlling this operation
write the data
to the output device and this
controlling operations would be carried
out based upon
a clock the clock is nothing but
a crystal controlled oscillator which we
have already seen in our previous
lectures
it produces pulses at regular intervals
and based upon the
the clock signals
the control bus operations would be
carried out by
the microprocessor
well now see what are the various
programmable controllers which are based
upon
the mic processor in the industry
basically
plc's that is a programmable logic
controllers
and microcontrollers are often being
used these two devices
are incorporating microprocessor as
their
cpu central processing unit
so what is the microcontroller the
microcontroller has
the central processor it has the memory
and
it has the input output ports so
together it is called as the
microcontroller
it is implementing
the functions of a computer and the
controller
but all these functions and all this
circuitry
is on a single chip that is
the uniqueness of the microcontroller
it is a very small device which can
easily
embed inside the equipment itself
so all the processing circuitry
memory and input output ports are
manufactured integrated on a single chip
itself
but the capability of microcontroller is
limited it is generally
programmed to carry out a few
applications
few operations a simple operation say
control
of temperature in in an electrical
furnace a simple operation
is there to control the temperature if
the
set temperature is more than then cut
off it
so for one or two applications the
microcontrollers are used
again i am giving the example of the
washing machine
so to control the operations of washing
machines which is having the limited
capability
we cannot change its program
it is dedicated to specific control
function
so generally microcontrollers are used
in automobiles
aircrafts and medical electronics
and majorly they are being used in the
home automation
home appliances
so as i mentioned they are very small
and can be embedded
in electromechanical system without
taking up much space
they are space effective very small
integrated compact devices
they need very little programmable
memory
memory is also required very less
so some of the standard microcontrollers
available in the market
uh can be seen on your screen these are
motorola
68 hd11 xylox
intel mcs51
and 96 series
the next type of controller is the
programmable logic controller
and it is often used in the
heavy industry heavy automation industry
we can say that any computer which is
having the
input output interface which can be used
to
communicate with the external devices
it's nothing but a programmable logic
controller but what is the difference of
a typical plc with
the micro controller or micro computer
is that
the computers or controllers are not
industrially
hardened they are not designed
to sustain in the harsh conditions
in the industry harsh conditions may be
very high currents high voltages
high temperature high humidity high
noise
vibrations so micro computers
may not sustain this harsh environment
so when we are designing spatial
microprocessor based device which will
sustain
all these harsh conditions that is
nothing but the programmable logic
controller
the plcs have electrically isolation
circuitry so we have seen one very
important
isolation circuitry that is a optical
isolators of toy
isolators
so these type of isolation circuitries
are
integrated in the plc to safeguard the
the circuitry of the plc from the
harmful signals
a typical definition of the plc can be
seen on your screen
it is a digital electronic device
it uses the programmable memory
to store the instructions and to
implement the functions such as
logic sequencing timing counting
and arithmetic words to control the
machines
and processes so i want i would like to
emphasize here that
these are very general these these
functions
are very general they are there in the
microprocessor
in microcomputer and in microcontroller
as well
but when we use these technology
especially to control the machines
and the processes then we then we
we are calling that device as the
programmable logic controller
a schematic of the arrangement of
various elements
of plc can be seen on your screen
here you can notice that
the plc has all the typical elements
which are there in a micro computer it
has
microprocessor communication
ports communication paths that is a
buses
memory but
you just notice that the plc's has
a power supply that is supporting the
memory
that is assisting the memory and that is
also
assisting the microprocessor it has
inbuilt power supply which is helping
the memory and microprocessor to survive
the plc's have the input output circuits
and dedicated input and industrially
hardened
output interfaces
so that the circuitry of the plc will be
safeguarded little more
details about the plc's can be seen on
your screen
see it has all the elements
of a typical microprocessor based system
that is cpu the clock
which is controlling the operations of
the cpu
the memory elements such as the
read-only memory
random access memory input output units
various buses input
system address bus system and the
control bus system
but as i mentioned it has the battery
which is supporting the memory the user
program
memory here
and the important thing is that we are
using
opto isolators in the plc system
opto isolators are protecting the plc
from very harsh
signals so the input output system
is having a buffer and the buffer is
attached to the opto isolator system
if the signals are in acceptable range
they will be buffered in a buffer
register
and then the through input output system
bus
it will be communicated inside the
circuitry
a typical plc can be seen
a photograph of a typical plc can be
seen on your screen
so it has the output
relay and input relay output
output terminals and input terminals
few more pictures of the plcs can be
seen on your screen
so this is the mitsubishi fx 1s 20 mr
you you can see the construction of the
plc is very rugged very robust
only that the interfaces are open to the
external world and the construction is
very compact very strong
we can collapse together many plcs and
they can be stored
in a in a rack on your screen you can
see
a rack with multiple number of plc's are
stored they are stationed
so let us summarize the basic functions
of the plcs
the plc is scanning a set of sensor
inputs
very rapidly and repetitively
so they are getting the inputs at a very
fast
rate and then they evaluate
that sensor input they carry out
the logic operations on that and
according to
the program written they are generating
the output
so where the plc's are being used plcs
are used in
automation in open loop it is a
sequential manner
they are also used in the assembly lines
in the industry the plc's has
multiple inputs and they do have the
multiple outputs
so the same plc can be connected to many
equipment
with multiple inputs can be taken in
inside
and the output can be given to the the
actuators
or the actuation devices
what are the various advantages of plcs
the plc is a very cost effective
it is a flexible and it has ability to
use similar system for other processes
the plc is not a very dedicated or a
special purpose device it is
general purpose device so as i mentioned
it is having multiple inputs and
multiple output
the same plc device can be utilized for
the other processes provided you have to
program it accordingly
it has capability to resist the impact
and vibrations
it has very good resistance towards
electrical and mechanical noise and it
can be
used in very high temperature so that's
why they are very popular
very important in the automation
industry
well with with this i would like to
stop for the introduction to
microprocessor technology
fine let us summarize uh this lecture
four
friends we have seen the important
building block
of a typical or mechatronics based
automated system
that is microprocessor we have seen its
importance
the microprocessor is the brain of the
automatic system
we studied the architecture of a
microprocessor
we have seen its elements
various modules the operations of
these modules and elements have been
studied
after that we learned about the
microcontroller
the microcontroller its definition and
its
its difference with the concept of the
microprocessor
then we have also seen the
microcomputers
its meaning and finally we studied
the plcs that is programmable logic
controllers
its elements configuration and operation
in lecture 5 of week 5
we will go ahead with programming
languages
which are used in designing of
microprocessors
we will have an introduction to the
programming languages
the number system what is the meaning of
low level programming language
what is the meaning of assembly language
and
in association with that we will have an
example we will
have a case study till then good bye
thank you
[Music]
you